Hey there, it's me.
Another day, another useful lesson from PREP.
Welcome back to our IELTS writing course.
To get a higher score in IELTS, you must use complex sentences.
A complex sentence combines a main idea with extra information.
Today, we will study the rules for three
types of grammar – relative clauses, contracted relative clauses, and conditionals.
First, let's look at the common structure of relative clauses.
Subject, verb, comma, who, which, or that.
Relative clauses start with words like who, which, or that.
Who describes a person?
Which describes an object?
However, which can also describe the entire idea before a comma.
That is used for both people and things,
but remember not to use that after a comma.
In IELTS Writing Task 1, relative clauses are
very useful in comparing data.
You can describe any information in the graph
by stating a date, and then compare it
to another data by adding a which clause.
Let's look at some examples.
According to the bar chart, by far the highest percentage is subject interest, at 40%,
which is only 2% higher than that of gaining qualifications.
Relative clauses can also be used to provide more information about a noun or a phrase.
For example, online applications allowed people who
could not go to their offices to work from home.
In this sentence, the relative clause explains more
about a specific group of people.
Without this clause, we wouldn't know why
these specific people were working remotely.
And finally, relative clauses are also used to
connect and show the relation between two phrases.
The word "which" refers to the entire situation mentioned before the comma,
using this structure connects the cause, bad communication, to the result, low productivity.
When a relative pronoun is a subject and
the verb is passive, we can contract the clause.
Let's look at this sentence in Sample Band 6 essay.
40% of people in the survey think
individuals should pay the costs of each course,
followed by employers at 35%.
In this sentence, followed by is a contracted relative clause.
The full version is, which is followed by.
When the relative pronoun is the subject of
the relative clause, and the verb is in
the passive form, the relative clause is contracted
to the past participle of the verb.
We have this structure that you can apply
easily in writing Task 1 essays,
subject, verb, followed by a noun or noun phrase.
However, please note that followed by is used
to say what comes after something else
in a list or ordered set of things.
Similarly, we have another common contracted
relative clause, subject, verb, compared with a noun or noun phrase.
In this structure, compared to with is also a contracted relative clause.
The full version is, which is compared to with.
This structure can be used to compare any two subjects.
This sentence can be rewritten as each course, compared with employers at 35%.
Conditionals are used to show a logical link between a condition and its result.
This is essential for describing processes or making arguments.
The structure is if or unless subject, verb, comma, subject, verb.
Please note that unless means if not.
In both cases, if you start the sentence
with the conjunction if or unless, you must
use a comma to separate the condition from the result.
Here are some examples.
If the jam is too thin, pectin is added to thicken the mixture.
This sentence is from a Writing Task 1
essay describing the process of making cherry jam.
Another example of conditional structure is This
sentence is the same as If authorities do
not implement stricter environmental regulations, large corporations will
continue to prioritise profit over sustainability.
Great job everyone!
Identifying these structures is the first step to using them.
Practice finding these in high-level model answers
and then try to build them into your own Task 1 and Task 2 responses.
Now let's have a quick review of what we learned today through some questions.
Today's lesson covered a lot, so make sure
to organise and review your notes to remember and apply the knowledge effectively.
You've all done well.
Now take some time to relax and get ready for the next lessons.
I am Anna, goodbye and see you next time.